在麦太即将临盆的时候
When Mrs. McBing was in labour…
一只胶兜在九龙上空飞过
A pan appeared in the sky.
沿荔枝角道直出大角咀道
It flied along Garden Street…
经好彩酒家左转花园街乐园牛丸王⋯
Turned left, and stopped at the Beefball King.
更正一下：
Correction:
先到街市大楼妹记鱼腩粥外边
It first arrived at the Market Building…
转呀，转⋯再更正一下：
Lingered a bit… Correction:
直出亚皆老街跨过火车桥右转太平道
It flied over the railway, turned right…
再右拐窝打老道向女人街方向飞⋯
And headed directly for the Bazaar.
飞呀，飞⋯
It flied on…
胶兜最后飞进广华医院候产房
At last coming into the maternity ward.
也就是在麦太右边额角上⋯
There, on the right hand side of Mrs. McBing.
更正：左边额角上⋯
Correction: Left hand side.
转呀，转⋯
The pan stayed.
麦太认定这是异像
Mrs. McBing, convinced that this was a miracle,
于是向额角上的胶兜许愿
Made a wish…
脑海中同时出现即将诞生的儿子容貌⋯
Thinking of her soon-to-be-born son.
希望他好聪明，读书好叻！
Please make him a clever and smart boy!
胶兜对麦太的愿望似乎没有反应
The pan didn't seem to hear her words.
于是她向胶兜补充说：
So Mrs. McBing amended her wish:
或者读书唔叻，工作叻呢？
Or make him a smart businessman?
又或者⋯
Or maybe…
又或者好靓仔，好靓仔
Or make him really handsome.
跟周润发，梁朝伟那么靓仔！
As handsome as Chow Yun Fat or Tony Leung!
胶兜仍然在转，毫无点头迹象
The pan didn't respond.
麦太一时心虚
Mrs. McBing, in panic…
赶忙趁胶兜落地前另许一个愿望：
Made a final amendment:
唔聪明唔靓仔也算了，只要福星高照
Her boy needed not to be smart or handsome
一世够运，逢凶化吉！
As long as luck be with him!
靠自己能力解决事情当然最好
It's nice to depend on oneself…
不过运气还是很重要的
But luck is essential still.
虽是说像梁朝伟周润发也行运定了
Of course Chow and Leung are lucky guys…
但总得要叻仔呀！
But then they are smart too!
最后，胶兜「𠼬督」一声落地
Finally, the pan dropped to the floor…
𠼬督？𠼬督，就是答应了
Mrs. McBing, believing her wish granted…
麦太想，这次走运了！
Thought that was magnificent!
可是答应了些什么呢？
But what had the pan granted her?
叻仔？好运？
A smart boy? A lucky boy?
还是似周润发？
Or a Chow look-alike?
为了纪念这赐福的胶兜
To commemorate this, Mrs. McBing…
麦太决定把儿子命名麦胶
Decided to name her son McNificent.
不行，胶胶声，多难听！
No! It's better to be humble!
还是唤他麦兜！
I'll name him McDull!
各位⋯
Dear all…
我就是险些给定名麦胶的小朋友⋯
I am the boy, no more McNificent…
麦兜！
I'm McDull!
麦太，没见面一阵
Oh dear,
怎么小腿粗起来了？
your calves have grown strong.
可怜呀，每天扑来扑去⋯
"I've been desperately…
替儿子找幼稚园！
looking for a school!
怎么不试一试好彩酒楼对面
Why not try the one…
旧中侨国货楼上的⋯
at the Emporium?
春田花花幼稚园？
The Spring Flower Kindergarten?
就是座落界限街南昌街交界⋯
Yeah! The one at the junction…
银城美食广场附近的⋯
Right next to Silver City Food Mall.
春田花花幼稚园？
The Spring Flower Kindergarten!
对！深水埗地铁站步行不用10分钟！
Only 10 minutes walk from the MTR Station!
春田花花幼稚园，师资优良⋯
Spring Flower Kindergarten, good environment…
而且还有西人教英文！
With white teachers for English class!
西人教英文？
White teachers for English class?
是呀！
Yeah!
春田花花，确有好多西人呀！
Spring Flower offers white teachers!
"鹅满是快烙滴好耳痛⋯"
"We are all happy children…"
"鹅闷天天一戏个窗！"
"We sing everyday!"
“鹅们在壳习，鹅闷载升胀⋯”
"We learn as we grow…"
"鹅闷是春天滴化！"
"We are the flowers of spring!"
这个猪样白兔小朋友⋯
This piggy kid in a rabbit outfit…
横看竖看也不像发哥伟仔的一个⋯
Who doesn't look the least like Chow or Leung…
就是我，麦兜
That's me, McDull.
这是我就读的幼稚园
This is my kindergarten.
校长是潮州人
The headmaster came from the countryside…
可能是潮州口音的关系
As a result, he speaks with an accent.
这么多年来⋯
For many years…
我其实不大明白他的说话
I had difficulty hearing him.
﹣蛋挞！　　﹣蛋挞！
- Tart!    - Tart!
﹣荔芋火鸭礼！　　﹣荔芋火鸭礼！
- Duck dumpling!    - Duck dumpling!
﹣忘记校训九十七⋯　　﹣忘记校训九十七⋯
- The 97 Rule…    - The 97 Rule…
也不能忘记校训九十八！
Shall be replaced by the 98 Rule!
好！各位同学⋯
Good, children!
今天的早会主要是跟大家分享
We are sharing an important issue…
一个重要主题：
this morning:
小朋友，这个月你们交过学费没有？
Children, have you handed in the school fee?
交过了！
Yes!
太好了！大家去上堂吧
Great! Now move to class.
你们可能觉得这间幼稚园很烂
You might conclude that this is a shabby school.
可是，对我和我一班同学
But, for me and my mates…
这儿是我们最快乐，最美丽的乐园⋯
This is the most beautiful paradise!
⋯还有一个很疼我们
…Also, there is Miss Chan.
就是有点游魂的Miss Chan
Who adores us in her absent-minded way.
她的志愿是做第二个王菲
Also, she is a Faye Wong wannabe.
做第二个陈慧琳也可以
Actually, Kelly Chan will do!
我们现在开始点名
Roll call now.
﹣麦唛同学！　　﹣到！
- McMug!    - Present!
﹣亚辉同学！　　﹣到！
- Fail!    - Present!
﹣菇时同学！　　﹣到！
- Goosie!    - Present!
﹣得巴同学！　　﹣到！
- Darby!    - Present!
﹣阿May同学！　　﹣到！
- May!    - Present!
﹣阿June同学！　　﹣到！
- June!    - Present!
﹣阿May同学！　　﹣到！
- May!    - Present!
﹣麦唛同学！　　﹣到！
- McMug!    - Present!
阿May同学！
May!
Miss Chan，我点过两次了！
Miss Chan, I've been called twice!
呀，真的吗？
Oops!
校长早晨！
Good morning, sir!
校长再见！
Good day, sir!
我们现在继续点名
Back to roll call.
﹣阿June同学！　　﹣到！
- Fail!    - Present!
﹣亚辉同学！　　﹣到！
﹣得巴同学！　　﹣到！
- Darby!    - Present!
﹣阿May同学！　　﹣到！
- May!    - Present!
﹣麦唛同学！　　﹣到！
- McMug!    - Present!
﹣菇时同学！　　﹣到！
- Goosie!    - Present!
还有谁没点过吗？
Have I missed anyone?
麦兜！
McDull!
麦兜同学！
麦唛呀，即是呢⋯
Hey, I don't understand…
我好像觉得呢⋯
I keep feeling that…
有什么人在喊我似的
Someone is calling me.
你们不要以为我心散
Don't think that I've been daydreaming.
其实我正在思考一个学术问题：
I was contemplating something academic:
橙，为什么会是「疴-烂-煮」呢？
How does this universe work?
妈妈说吃橙可通大便
I mean, I ate 6 oranges that morning…
「疴」这个我明白，可是「烂-煮」呢？
And my stomach wouldn't stop.
还有这个「芭-娜-娜」香蕉
Then I ate 3 bananas this morning.
为什么雨伞又会是「暗-芭-娜-娜」呢？
Again my stomach wouldn't stop…
我「暗」的「暗」掉一条蕉
It just wouldn't stop!
至多是疴烂煮，怎么会下起雨来呢？
How are these two things related?
这世界还有很多事情我弄不明白
There are so many things that I don't understand.
但我不害怕
But I am not afraid.
我想，有天我念完幼稚园
One day, when I finish kindergarten…
升小学，上中学
I shall move up…
再念大学⋯
And get my degree.
当我大学毕业的时候
When I graduate from university, I know…
我知道我会明白一切！
I shall understand everything!
那时候⋯
And then …
我买所房子给妈妈！
I will buy my mother a house!
幼稚园楼下，由校长兼营的茶餐厅
Our headmaster runs a tea stand…
我们一班同学下课后经常光顾
Which we kids frequent after class.
﹣鱼蛋粗面，麻烦你　　﹣粗面买光了
- Fishball noodle, please.    - No noodle left.
﹣那样子⋯来碗鱼蛋河粉吧　　﹣鱼蛋买光了
- Fishball rice noodle then.    - No fishball left.
﹣那么⋯金钱肚粗面好了　　﹣粗面买光了
- Chicken wing noodle then.    - No noodle left.
﹣那么要鱼蛋油面吧　　﹣鱼蛋买光了
- How about fishball congee?    - No fishball left.
怎么都买光了？
Nothing left today?
﹣来个墨鱼丸粗面吧　　﹣粗面买光了
- How about beef noodle?    - No noodle left.
又买光了？
Again?
﹣麻烦来碗鱼蛋濑吧　　﹣鱼蛋买光了
- Fried chicken wing with fishball…    - No fishball left.
麦兜呀，鱼蛋跟粗面都买光了
Hey, fishball and noodle are both gone…
即是所有鱼蛋跟粗面的配搭都没了
You can't combine them with other things.
没有那些配搭吗？
Can't combine them?
麻烦你，净要鱼蛋吧。鱼蛋买光了。
- A bowl of fishball then.    - No fishball left.
﹣那么净要粗面呢？　　﹣粗面买光了
- A bowl of noodle?    - No noodle left.
看到这里⋯
By now…
大家大概都知道我是个怎么样的叻仔
you can probably tell how smart I am.
那时候我无忧无虑，万事无所谓﹣﹣
Nothing worried me, all things were fine.
鱼蛋买光了？那么粗面吧
No fishball left? Let's get some noodle.
麦兜，射呀！
Shoot, Dull!
看着自己每天疴烂煮⋯
Watching myself grow and grow…
每天长肉⋯
Everyday…
我感到充满力量！
I feel full of strength!
世界好美丽！
The world is beautiful!
有一首歌，Miss Chan唱的好听
There is a song Miss Chan loves…
我时常想着学习
Which I always want to learn…
可每次我总唱成「疴」什么什么的⋯
But it just comes out different.
是All Things Bright and Beautiful吧？
You mean "All Things Bright and Beautiful"?
是的，一切都好！
Yes, all are fine!
世上一切，一切一切⋯
All things on earth…
所有那些，都好！
They are fine!!
一、二、三、四、五、六、七⋯
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7…
多劳多得！
No pain no gain!
星期一至星期七⋯多劳多得！
Monday till Sunday… No pain no gain!
这位喊得特劲的中年母猪
The middle-aged swine is Mrs. McBing,
就是我妈妈麦太
my mother…
我妈妈真的很劲
A brilliant woman…
一个女人背起整个世界！
carrying the world!
是的，我妈妈真的很厉害
Yes, she is really something.
除了兼任保险，地产经纪及trading⋯
She works in insurance, real estate and trading.
她还趁高科技热潮搞了个烹饪网站⋯
At the height of IT, she even sets up her cooking site…
www.麦太世界.com
www.MrsMcBing.com
她做的菜，同样厉害
Offering brilliant dishes.
欢迎大家收看《麦太世界》
Welcome to "Mrs. Mc Can Cook."
今日为大家介绍一个⋯
Today we're doing a simple dish,
简单别致的小菜纸包鸡
Paper Chicken.
家中小朋友一定好喜欢
Kids at home would love it.
材料很简单：一个鸡包
The ingredient: a chicken bun.
将鸡包底部的纸撕下来⋯慢慢地撕
Slowly, we tear the paper away from the bun.
就会得到一张鸡包纸
Now we have a bun paper.
把鸡包纸，一反反转
Turn the paper over like this…
这一味纸包鸡就完成了，很容易是吧？
Voila! Simple, isn't it?
多谢大家收看
Thank you, everyone!
好高兴这么快又跟大家见面
How time flies since last episode!
接下来我会教大家整一味纸鸡包
Now we shall do a Paper Bun.
材料也很简单，只需要白纸一张
The ingredient takes only a paper.
只要把这纸这样子⋯
Do it like this…
一个纸鸡包就这样完成了
And we have a Paper Bun.
各位小朋友，像鸡包不像呀？
Isn't this a lovely bun?
现在要教大家一味别致小菜﹣
A novelty today for everyone:
包鸡纸包鸡包纸包鸡
Chicken Bun Paper Bunning a Bun.
首先将纸包鸡小心撕开
First, unwrap the chicken from the paper.
大家就会有一张纸包鸡及一块鸡
Now we have a paper and a piece of chicken.
接着把鸡包纸这样子包起那块鸡
Use the bun paper to wrap up the chicken like this…
再依照这样子用包鸡纸把它包起
And then wrap it like this…
一味「包鸡纸包鸡包纸包鸡」完成了！
The delicious Chicken Bun Paper Bunning a Bun!
真的很简单吧？
Such a simple dish!
还真有一块鸡吃呢！
See if the chicken is good!
今日为大家介绍一味⋯
Kids are bound to love…
小朋友一定喜欢的⋯
today's dish…
鸡包包鸡包包鸡包纸包纸⋯
Bunning a Chicken Bun Paper…
包鸡包鸡包纸包鸡
Bunning the Paper Chicken.
做法亦很简单
It takes simple work.
只要将鸡包包住个鸡包
Use the chicken bun to bun…
再包住个鸡包⋯
the chicken bun…
包住张鸡包纸
Then use the chicken bun paper to…
再包包包包包住个纸鸡包
bun and bun…
再包包包，纸纸纸
Paper, bun, bun, paper, bun…
纸包纸，纸包鸡，鸡包纸，纸包鸡⋯
Paper, chicken, bun, bun, chicken…
可我妈妈也有她温柔的一面
But my mother has her tender side.
例如每晚睡觉前，她都会说故事给我听
Every night, she tells me a story before sleep.
从前，有个小朋友撒谎；有一天⋯
Once upon a time, a boy lied. One day…
他死了！
He died.
从前，有个小朋友很勤力念书⋯
Once upon a time, a boy studied hard.
他长大后，发财了！
He grew up and got rich.
从前，有个小朋友不孝，有天⋯
Once upon a time, a boy was naughty. One day…
他扭了脚骹！
He twisted his ankle.
妈妈，我想睡觉
Mother, I want to sleep.
从前，有个小朋友早睡晚起；第二天⋯
Once upon a time, a boy slept a lot. Next day…
他死了！
He died.
我妈妈就是这样子，一切都那么直接
That is my mother's direct approach.
她爱得我直接⋯
Her love for me is direct.
对我的期望直接
Her expectation of me is direct.
对她，一、二、三、四、五、六、七
For her, it is always…
没有不成的事
"no pain no gain".
可有些事情，要是真的不成呢？
But there are things that simply cannot be gained.
日子一天一天的过
Days come and go.
首先是周润发事件⋯
Talking about Chow look-alike…
拜托不要再提了！
You still think it's going to happen?
至于好运⋯
When it comes to luck…
我用一双童子手替妈妈抽的六合彩号码
The lottery numbers that mother obliges to draw…
奇迹般似的一个号码也没中过！
Failed even to bring her one cent!
叻仔？
As for being smart…
我也试过努力念书，可是⋯
I did try hard, but then…
可是⋯我们仍然有梦
But then, I still have dreams.
马尔代夫，座落于印度洋的世外桃源
Maldives, a world outside our world.
蓝天白云，椰林树影，水清沙幼
The sky blue, clouds white, the trees tall and water bright.
七彩缤纷的珊瑚，目不暇给的热带鱼
The colourful world of the tropical sea.
充满赤道活力的原始海洋，脱离繁嚣
The primitive ocean of primitive energy.
体验热情如火的风土人情
Experience a world that knows no boundary!
享受一个脱俗出尘的梦幻之旅
Enjoy a trip to your ideal world.
犀利旅行社，旅行社牌照号码350999
Brilliant Touring Agency, license no. 350999
妈妈你知道马尔代夫在哪里吗？
Mother, you know where Maldives is?
很远的
Far.
有多远？
How far?
得搭飞机
You need to fly there.
妈妈你会带我去吗？
Mother will you take me there?
会！发财了再说吧
One day when I am rich.
那么妈妈你什么时候发？
When will you get rich?
快了⋯
Soon…
发梦呀！
In my dream!
校长早晨！
Good morning, sir!
校长再见！
Good day, sir!
你最喜爱的地方是哪儿？
Where is your favourite place?
我最喜爱的地方是日本
My favourite place is Japan.
那儿有Disneyland和Hello Kitty Land
They have Disneyland and Hello Kitty Land.
我这个发夹也是在那儿买的
I bought my hairpin there.
我最喜爱的地方是加拿大
My favourite place is Canada.
婆婆跟舅父他们都在加拿大
Grandma and my uncles live there.
我最喜爱的地方是泰国
My favourite place is Bangkok.
那儿有很好多水上活动，还有鱼翅吃
They have water sports and shark's fin soup.
我最喜爱的地方⋯
My favourite place is that…
就是那间什么！
What's-its-name.
那儿有欢乐天地，还有美食广场
They have Fun World and Food Mall.
那儿的海南鸡饭很大碟的
Their chicken rice fills you up.
对了，那地方叫银城中心
Right, that's Silver City Centre.
那店子的饭很多，很大碟的！
They serve huge bowls of rice.
不过说到我最想去的地方，那可厉害了
As for the place I most want to go, wow!
那儿蓝天白云，椰林树影，水清沙幼
There, the sky is blue, clouds white, the trees tall…
座落于印度洋的世外桃源
It is a world outside our world.
衰仔，快点起床上学
Rise and shine, kiddo.
咦？
Oh?
妈妈！
Mother!
开点药给他吃就没事了
Take some medicine and he'll be fine.
医生，吃了药会不会有那个什么的？
Will he not what after the medicine?
不会！
No!
那么吃药用不用那个什么的？
Need he not what for the medicine?
不用！给他打口针吧！
No! I'll give him a shot.
怎么？得打针？
A shot?
他最怕打针的了
He's scared of shots.
那么他怕不怕死？
Is he scared of dying?
没事吧？快点先把药水喝掉！
How are you doing? Take the medicine.
妈妈我不想喝药水
Mother, I don't want medicine.
不要呀妈妈，我不喝呀
Please mother, no.
我不喝士多啤梨药水呀！
I don't want the strawberry drink!
别哭了，不喝药水病不会好的
You won't get well without the medicine.
乖乖，病好了妈妈带你去马尔代夫
Sweetie, we will go to Maldives once you get well.
真的吗？
Really?
妈妈什么时候骗过你？
Has mother ever lied before?
乖，先把药水喝掉
Now, drink up.
好呀，马尔代夫！
Yes, Maldives!
马尔代夫！
Maldives!
妈妈，那么我们什么时候去？
Mother, when will we go?
你先把药水喝掉，病好了我就去订机票
I will book the ticket once you get well.
来，多喝一点！
Come on, drink up!
妈妈，你看！
Look, mother!
妈妈你看，我病好了！
Mother, I am well!
我把药都吃光了
I've taken all the medicine.
家中的东西有什么没给你吃光的？
But you've taken everything edible at home.
这次不同呀，原来这么一大樽的
You see, the whole bottle was filled…
我喝一格，又喝一格，又喝一格⋯
And I gulped it down bit by bit…
就给我喝光了！
I did it!
喝光了就叻仔了！
Now I am a good boy!
喝光了就病好了！
Now I am not sick!
妈妈呀⋯
Mother…
什么事？
What?
我们什么时候去马尔代夫？
When are we going to Maldives?
什么马尔代夫？
Maldives?
你说我病好带我去马尔代夫的呀！
You said we would go once I got well.
马尔代夫，椰林树影，水清沙幼⋯
Maldives, where the trees tall and water bright…
座落于印度洋的世外桃源呀！
The world outside our world!
想不到你还有点文采
Those words have flair.
说得不错呀！
I am happy for you.
我不是光说的呀，妈妈你说过⋯
Mother, you promised…
我病好了带我去马尔代夫的！
We'd go to Maldives once I got well.
我是说发了财就带你去
I meant once I get rich.
不是的，妈妈你说我病好了就去的
No, that wasn't what you meant.
你分明讲过病好了就去马尔代夫的
You said we'd go once I got well.
你讲过的！
You promised!
好了，别哭了
Now stop crying.
带你去马尔代夫好了
We will go to Maldives.
﹣真的吗？　　﹣对
- Really?    - Yes.
什么时候去？
When?
发财再说
Once I get rich.
你早发财了⋯
But you are rich.
好了好了，发财了
Sure, sure, I am rich.
我们下个星期去，好了吧？
We will go next week, ok?
太好了！
Bravo!
麦唛，我是麦兜呀
This is McDull.
是这样子的，我明天就飞了
Hey, I'm leaving tomorrow.
﹣对　　﹣⋯是吗？
- Yes…    - Is that right?
飞机餐很难吃的吗？
The food on board is horrible?
也得吃呀！
Be it so!
难道自己带东西上去吃吗？
We couldn't bring our own food, right?
还在讲？
Still chatting away?
快点帮手执行李
You need to pack.
跟我向他们说，我明天去马尔代夫了
Tell them I'm going to Maldives tomorrow.
那边蓝天白云，椰林树影⋯
Where the trees tall and water bright…
还在讲！
Hey, you!
来了！
Coming!
要执行李了，回来再跟你说吧
I need to pack now. Talk to you later.
再见！
See you!
妈妈，我得把出世纸带着吗？
Mother, do I need to bring my birth certificate?
也要的
I guess so.
那么成绩表呢？
And school report?
成绩表就不用了
We don't need that.
太好了！吓得我！
Wow, I'm saved!
找到了！
I found it!
出世纸给我找到了！
I found my birth certificate!
妈妈你替我收好它别抛掉
Mother, you keep it and don't lose it…
抛掉就去不成了
Or else we're stuck.
早机去，晚机返
Leave on the morning, return at night.
妈妈说这样才够精明
Mother said that'd make things worthy.
就这样⋯
Hence…
我过了我小时候最精明⋯
The most beautiful day in my childhood experience…
最美丽的一天
Passed.
依你说，纸是否可以包着鸡呢？
Do you think paper is a good chicken wrapper?
也可以的⋯
Maybe.
特别是小小一块的
If only for one small piece.
妈妈晚安！
- Goodnight, mother!    - Goodnight!
最新消息
The Hong Kong…
奥运滑浪风帆选手李丽珊五场四胜
windsurfing athlete San San Li…
夺得香港历史上第一面奥运金牌！
Has just won the first gold medal in Hong Kong history!
消息说当李丽珊获悉自己稳夺金牌后
San San, when confirmed her winning…
激动地对在场记者表示她今次的成绩⋯
Told reporters that her result…
足以证明香港运动员不是腊鸭！
Helps prove that Hong Kong athletes are horrible…
﹣对不起，应该　　﹣是垃圾，不是腊鸭！
Excuse me, it should be "honourable".
﹣对不起，应该　　﹣不是垃圾，也不是腊鸭！
Hong Kong athletes are honourable athletes.
特别报告完毕
End of special report.
妈妈好像又有计了
Then, mother seemed inspired.
靓仔，好运，叻仔⋯
Handsome, lucky, smart…
好像都没希望了
So much for those plans.
是不是可以靠手瓜呢？
Now how about something physical?
于是，一个梦还没醒⋯
And so, while one dream lingers on…
我又得到另一个梦
Another one begins.
应该是脚瓜
It's about the Calf!
我知道一点也不容易
I know it is not easy.
我知道要找到黎根绝对不容易
I know it is not easy to find Logan.
我知道要他收我做徒弟更加不容易
I know it is not easy for him to take me in.
但无论多不容易，我都要试一试
No matter how difficult this is…
我要黎根收我做徒弟！
Logan will be my master!
无论几辛苦，我一定要得到奥运金牌！
I shall get an Olympic medal!
长洲！长洲！
Cheung Chau!
你孕育了珊珊！你也会孕育我！
You raised San San, now you will raise me!
当我站在奥运会颁奖台上
When I receive my Olympic medal…
我会举起金牌跟全世界说：
I shall tell the world:
香港运动员不是垃圾！
HK athletes are honourable athletes!
长洲，我终于来到长洲了！
Cheung Chau, I finally make it here.
长洲，我得亲吻这片圣洁的土地！
I must kiss this holy land!
小朋友，这儿是南丫岛呀！
Kiddo, this is Lamma Island.
南Y岛？它也孕育了周润发！
Lamma Island? Where Chow Yun Fat grew up?
想不到我黎根避进南丫岛也给你发现
I came into hiding on this island…
小朋友，你知道什么是狗仔队吧？
To stay away from the paparazzi.
加上总有小朋友及家长来说要拜我为师
And so many kids came to seek me out.
我才过来南Y岛避一避
So I came to live here.
至于拜师的事⋯
You want me to be your master?
拜你个头！
Forget it!
你们这些住香港岛的小朋友骄生惯养
You city kids are all spoiled…
怎么吃得苦？
Good for nothing!
想跟珊珊般得奥运金牌？
You want to get an Olympic medal too?
别作梦了！
Dream on!
小朋友，你看！
Kiddo, look!
这个⋯
This calf…
这脚瓜⋯好粗好大！比一节瓜还要大！
So thick, so strong!
脚瓜的肌肉非常结实⋯
And so muscular!
青筋凸现，钢线似的
With steely veins running down…
每一条脚毛都硬似铁钉
Hair sticking out like wire…
脚趾甲有一寸厚，究竟⋯
And those tough toenails!
要行过几多座山⋯
How many hills must it travel…
跨过几多个海⋯
How many seas must it pass…
吃过几多苦头⋯
How much pain must it bear…
才可以练成这举世无双的脚瓜？
Before a calf becomes a calf?
我⋯我一定要练成这脚瓜！
I shall have this calf!
师傅！
Master!
我可以去小个便吗？
Can I take a pee?
每次唱这首歌，我都会急小便
Whenever I sing this song, I need to pee.
现在先去，一回恐怕还是会急
Taking a pee first would not help.
但是我现在一定要唱这首歌
But I must sing it now.
希望可以改变黎根对我的看法
With this song, I hope…
我要用这歌打动黎根
Logan will think better of me.
我要黎根收我做徒弟！
Logan will be my master!
歌，是这样唱的⋯
The song goes like this…
「大包，整多两笼」
"Big bun, have two more…"
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
"Forget about indigestion."
「大包，整多两笼」
"Big bun, have two more…"
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
"Forget about indigestion."
「大包，整多两笼」
"Big bun, have two more…"
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
"Forget about indigestion."
「食晒个包，脚瓜大个」
"Eat the bun, grow a calf…"
「孝顺我阿妈」
"Respect my mother."
「食晒个包，脚瓜硬朗」
"Eat the bun, toughen my calf…"
「再奉献国家」
"Serve my country."
「大包，整多两笼」
"Big bun, have two more…"
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
"Forget about indigestion."
「大包，整多两笼」
"Big bun, have two more…"
「大包，整多两笼唔怕滞」
"Forget about indigestion."
黎根听完歌以后，表情有点古怪⋯
Logan looks strange after the song.
我一定要好好把握这个机会
I must grab my chance.
师傅！你收我做徒弟吧！
Master! Please be my master!
你唔收我做徒弟，我一世都这么跪着！
Or let me kneel here forever!
起来呀！
Get up…
多谢师傅！
Thank you master!
不⋯我是叫你扶我起来呀！
Silly, help me get up.
不成了！我的脚瓜太痹了！
My calf has gone numb!
我将今天发生的事讲给妈妈听
I tell mother what happened today.
妈妈一句话也没说
She won't say a word…
从冰箱内拿了只雪鸡出来解冻
But starts to defreeze a chicken.
晚饭时，妈妈倒了三杯米酒
At dinner, mother offers 3 glasses of wine…
又将几只橙和蒸好的鸡放到祖先前
Oranges and the chicken to the ancestral tablet.
妈妈叫我跪低，向祖先请请。
Mother then tells me to kneel down.
妈妈跟着又念念有词的
She mumbles something when…
然后我们一起向祖先再拜了几拜
We pay our respect to our ancestors.
妈妈蹲低把酒洒到地上
As mother pours the wine on the floor…
庄重而温柔地跟我说：
She says in her solemn, tender voice:
以后生生性性
Be good,
跟师傅学习，光宗耀祖！
learn with the master and honour the ancestors.
妈妈在长洲找了间酒楼摆拜师宴
In honour of my master, mother throws a banquet.
因为我是师傅最后一个入室弟子
As I am the last disciple of the master…
到贺的乡绅父老特别多
Everyone on Cheung Chau comes.
想不到黄德森也来了
San San's lover thinks…
还赞我背上的肉厚
I have a nice thick back.
珊珊因为去了集训，没来
San San is in training and couldn't come.
麦唛，菇时跟得巴都来了
All my mates are there too…
还带着成绩表，奖牌和大包
Bringing school report, medals and big buns.
他们都希望黎根也可以收他们做徒弟
They hope Logan will take them in also.
吃过鸡丝翅，就是拜师仪式
After the soup, the ceremony begins.
妈妈倒了杯茶给我，让我给师傅喝
Mother pours a cup of tea and I offer it to the master.
我千辛万苦来长洲找黎根⋯
After all the hardship looking for Logan…
我终于可以跟珊珊一起练滑浪风帆了！
Now I can windsurf together with San San!
我将茶递给黎根，黎根他⋯
I offer the tea to Logan…
师傅他把茶喝了，正式收我做徒弟
He drinks the tea and becomes my master.
宾客们好像都很高兴
All the guests look happy.
长洲的乡绅父老拍掌拍得特别落力
And everyone from Cheung Chau applauds.
多谢各位赏面！多谢各位！
Thank you for honouring me!
在下平生有两项称得上得意的绝技
In my life, I have two skills that I'm proud of.
第一项，是滑浪风帆！
One is windsurfing.
我把它传给外甥女珊珊了
That I have passed onto San San.
另一项绝技，我打算传给这个新徒弟⋯
The other, I shall pass onto my new disciple…
希望他把长洲人世世代代的绝技
Let him show the world…
发扬光大！
what a marvelous skill that is!
请问那是什么绝技呢？
Can you tell us what skill is that?
第二项绝技，就是⋯
That is…
抢包山！
Bun snatching!
抢包山？
Bun snatching?
年轻观众可能不知「抢包山」何物
"Bun Snatching", for our uninformed audience…
抢包山乃长洲独有传统节日
Is a unique Cheung Chau tradition.
每年农历四月
Each year, in the fourth month,
长洲居民均举办太平清醮
Cheung Chau people…
于北帝庙前搭起三座包山
Set up 3 stacks of bun to celebrate.
什么是包山呢？
Stacks of bun?
顾名思义⋯
Literally speaking…
包山就是一座由好多好多包砌起的山！
A stack of bun is a stack of many buns!
一座包山，起码六、七层楼高⋯
Each stack coming up to 6, 7 storeys.
你可以想像一下包山有多高了吧？
Imagine how high that is.
抢包山，就是要把包山上的包抢到手！
Bun snatching is to snatch those buns!
锣鼓响起
When the time comes,
数以百计的青年一涌而上抢包
hundreds of youth would rush up…
抢得位置愈高的包，就是愈大的祝福
The higher the bun you snatch, the more blessed you are.
更可以表现自己的不凡身手
And the more praise you get.
在1978年两座包山忽然倒下，多人重伤
In 1978, 2 stacks tumbled down, hurting many.
「抢包山」从此被禁！
"Bun Snatching" was thus banned!
而长洲独有的传统，亦渐被遗忘
And the unique tradition is lost.
奥运金牌⋯这一世是没有机会的了
The Olympic medal… it has slipped away.
每个星期六我都搭船过长洲
Every Saturday, I'd take a ferry to Cheung Chau…
去学抢包山⋯
to practice bun snatching.
一项没有奖牌，没有对手，没有比赛⋯
A game with no medal, no competitor, no competition…
甚至没有人知道是运动的运动
A game nobody knows of.
更坏的是，连包山也没有！
A game with no bun to snatch!
师傅只是叫我去他的家⋯
All I do is to go to the master's home…
在组合柜爬来爬去
and crawl around the shelf.
碰！三番！
My win!
别躲懒！继续练！
Keep going, lazy bone!
一天，珊珊到了师传家！
One day, San San arrives!
珊珊！我的师姐珊珊！
San San, my idol!
可以看见珊珊⋯
Seeing San San…
这几个星期爬得再辛苦也是值得的！
Makes me forget all these weeks' hard work.
珊珊！
San San!
珊你个头！继续练习！
San yourself! Work!
还不去？
You hear me?
珊珊没看见我这个师弟
So San San leaves without seeing me.
我只有死死气再爬上组合柜
In despair, I crawl up the shelf.
我咁大个仔，什么「头」也给骂过⋯
I have had a lot of things said to me…
不知道为什么
but "San yourself"…
「珊你个头」却特别刺耳
hurts like never before.
我⋯我⋯
I… I…
我唔学抢包山了！
I am quitting!
其实今天是我第一次近距离见黎根
Today is the first time I sit down with Logan.
他恐怕都有五十岁了
He must be around 50,
却还是一副孩子脸
with a baby face.
鸡尾包！新鲜出炉！
Fresh from the oven!
其实鸡尾包呢⋯
This thing…
你说这似不似鸡尾？
What does it look like?
麦兜他学东西⋯还可以
Dull… he's not a bad student.
黎根接着说了一大堆话⋯
Logan then proceeds to tell me a lot…
他的抱负，他对麦兜的期望
His ambition, his expectation of Dull.
他说他会把他所识的毫不保留教给麦兜
He says he'll teach all he knows to Dull.
黎根越说越兴奋，直到双眼发光
The more he talks, the more excited he gets.
他又说滑浪风帆并不是他最犀利的项目
He tells me windsurfing is not his strongest.
他最大强项是抢包山
His strongest is really bun snatching…
他说抢包山结合了南拳
Something combining Fist,
神功戏和现代器械操
ritual and gymnastic.
他说抢包山才是他一生最大成就
He says bun snatching is his lifelong achievement.
缩脚，唔该！
Move your feet!
你看！
Look!
这脚瓜⋯好粗好大！比一节瓜还要大！
This calf… so thick, so strong!
脚瓜的肌肉非常结实⋯
And so muscular!
青筋凸现，钢线似的
With steely veins running down…
每一条脚毛都硬似铁钉
Hair sticking out like wire…
脚趾甲有一寸厚，究竟⋯
And those tough toenails!
要走过几多座山
How many hills must it travel…
跨过几多个海
How many seas must it pass…
吃过几多苦头
How much pain must it bear…
才可以练成这举世无双的脚瓜？
Before a calf becomes a calf?
我个仔⋯
My son…
你个仔，他日都会有这只大脚瓜
Your son, he will get this calf.
其实我也不知道个仔要这么粗的脚瓜⋯
I have no idea why would Dull need…
有什么用
such a calf.
可是看见那些凸现的青筋，不知怎样⋯
But, looking at those steely veins…
我想起麦兜的爸爸，阿炳。
I am reminded of Dull's pa, Bing.
我找来找去也找不到那部电子英文辞典
The electronic dictionary cannot be found.
跑哪去了？
Where could it be?
难道⋯不会吧？
Could it be that… ?
想不到真的让妈妈拿去了。吓得我！
So mother has been using the dictionary?
妈妈怎么会写起英文信？
But why is she writing in English?
信很短
The letter is short.
我猜是妈妈用电子辞典逐个字译成英文
Mother must have translated it word by word.
于是我又用电子辞典把信译回中文
I use the machine to turn it back into Chinese.
信，是妈妈写给奥委会主席的
It is addressed to the Olympic Committee Chairman.
「亲爱的主席：」
"Dear Chairman:"
「你好吗？我很好！」
"How are you? I am fine."
「你吃包吗？我吃包！」
"You like bun? I like bun!"
「我们居住在香港这里的人，很爱吃包」
"We Hong Kong people here love bun."
「小笼包，上海包，广东包，莲蓉包」
"Buns of all sorts."
「好朋友，我认为」
"Dear friend,"
抢劫那些包，十分重要！
"It is important to snatch buns."
「也算是运动，就真！」
"It is a game, no joke."
「要大力！大吃晚上的粥，和大节瓜！」
"One needs energy, and many night congee."
「按照我愚蠢的见解⋯」
"In my stupid opinion…"
抢劫那些包，是奥运会比赛。
"Snatching bun is an Olympic game."
让全世界的体育家，抢过！
"Let athletes all over the world snatch!"
「世界便和平！」
"And there will be peace."
「你有孩子吗？」
"Do you have children?"
「我有一个孩子，麦兜」
"I have a boy, Dull."
终于讲到我了！
She's talking about me!
「他是一个好男孩」
"He is a good boy."
「他非常懂得抢劫那些包」
"He knows how to snatch buns."
「有一天，我看见他，抢劫包⋯」
"One day, I can see him snatching buns…"
「抢了一个奥运金牌」
"Ending up snatching an Olympic medal."
「那便是一个母亲能够有的最大的安慰」
"That is the biggest comfort a mother can get."
「孩子的才干，得到了世界人类的知道」
"Let the world know the talent of your children."
「父母愿意做什么的东西都得」
"Parents will do anything for that."
「于是我写了这忽然间的信给你」
"That is why I write you this sudden letter."
「虽然你不知道我是什么微细的东西」
"Although you don't know humble things like me."
「但我的孩子很大，很大！」
"But my boy is big, very big."
「有一天，你都会知道」
"One day, you will know him too."
「多谢合作！」
"Thank you for your cooperation."
「你忠实的，麦太」
"Yours faithfully, Mrs. Mc."
看完妈妈的信
After reading mother's letter…
我决定回长洲继续学捡包山
I go back to Cheung Chau to practice.
我不是为了见珊珊
Not because of San San.
我并不知道为什么要抢那些包
I don't know why I want to snatch a bun.
我也不相信抢包山会成为奥运项目
And I don't think it will ever become an Olympic sport.
可是，我依然努力练习抢包山
But I keep learning.
因为，我爱我妈妈
Because I love my mother.
师傅说我攀爬功夫已经不错
Master thinks my crawling has passed.
可以开始教我「十二路抢包手」
Now I'll learn the "12 Bun Snatching Hands".
师傅说当年师祖要出这套
Master says these 12 hands,
「十二路抢包手」⋯
in its prime…
连林世荣也大大赞好
Was much admired by Butcher Lin!
后来麦嘎告诉我⋯
Later, I learn from McMug…
林世荣即是猪肉荣，是黄飞鸿的徒弟
Butcher Lin was a disciple of the great Kung Fu king.
我不知道师傅像不像黄飞鸿
I don't know much about Kung Fu kings…
我却肯定像一块猪肉
But I must be the ultimate pork…
我是一块堵住两个包
The pork that struts about
在长洲转来转去的猪肉
with buns in hands.
我一边练习，一边胡思乱想；始终⋯
My mind boggles as I practice, after all…
我还是不大喜欢抢包
I am not a fan of bun snatching.
我只是爱我妈妈
I am only doing this for mother.
于是我咬实牙根⋯
Hence I hang on…
一步一步，一爪一爪⋯
Step by step, claw by claw…
我最后终于练成「十二路抢包手」
I make it pass the "12 Bun Snatching Hands".
喂，我是麦兜
This is Dull.
刚才的是小朋友麦兜，我是大个佬麦兜
Dull the big guy, not Dull the boy.
小朋友麦兜和大个佬麦兜除了声音不同⋯
The two Dulls have different voices, and then…
小朋友麦兜的世界仍然有好多幻想
Dull the boy's world is still filled with fantasy…
仍然有好多希望
Filled with hopes.
希望⋯失望⋯
Hope… Disappointment…
希望⋯
Hope…
失望
Disappointment.
久而久之，就变成大个佬麦兜
On and on, he became Dull the big guy.
我现在还是多说点小朋友麦兜
But I shall tell more about Dull the boy.
小朋友麦兜仍然希望希望⋯
Dull the boy hoped a lot.
希望真的有圣诞老人
He hoped there WAS a Santa Claus.
而且好想试试圣诞火鸡的滋味
And he hoped to eat a Christmas turkey.
对，那时我还没吃过火鸡
Right, I haven't eaten any turkey then.
关于火鸡的一切⋯
Everything about turkey…
圣诞树上一闪一闪的饰物
The sparkling tinkling Christmas tree…
就像天上掉落的星星
Like stars falling from the sky…
落到火炉旁边
Coming down by the fireplace.
一片片比外边的雪还要白的鸡胸肉⋯
Each slice of meat looks purer than snow.
就在我们跟前
Right in front of us…
香气直入灵魂⋯
The aroma attacks our soul…
连守在灵魂旁边的天使都醒过来
Waking even the guardian angels.
围住这香而圣洁的肉⋯
Who float around the aromatic and holy dish…
在圣诞夜中飞呀，飞⋯
Floating in the Christmas night, floating…
这关于火鸡的一切，不过是我的想像
All this about turkey was only my imagination.
我从来没吃过火鸡⋯
I had never eaten a turkey.
连它的气味也没嗅过
I had never even smelt one.
妈妈说火鸡太大
Mother claimed turkey was too big.
我们一家两口，吃不下
The two of us would never finish it.
有年圣诞节妈妈买了半只烤鸭庆祝
One Christmas we celebrated with roast duck.
当时的我，十分十分失望
I was really, really disappointed.
又有一年，一间百货公司结业
Another year, she bought a mini-oven at 60% off…
妈妈以四折买了个小小焗炉
At a closedown sale.
可能因为买了焗炉而技痒
Thanks to the oven…
那日妈妈竟然跟我说⋯
Mother decided one day…
让我们明天去超级市场揪火鸡
We would go shopping for a turkey.
我跟妈妈把火鸡揪回家的路上⋯
On the way home, with turkey in hand…
是我生命中最开心的时刻
That was the happiest moment in my life.
火鸡终于解冻了
The turkey was ready.
我学着妈妈，把双手涂满盐⋯
Following mother, with salt on both hands…
在火鸡丰厚的鸡胸上擦呀，擦
I rubbed the turkey's thick chest.
联火鸡时⋯
When sewing up…
妈妈不留神漏出了火鸡内的洋葱粒
Some of the stuffing…
红萝卜粒
leaked out.
我说：火鸡「疴烂煮」！
I cried: the turkey's stomach won't stop!
好勉强把火鸡塞进焗炉内
We managed to stuff the turkey into the oven.
12月24日
24th, December
上升的白烟跟奇异的焦味拨动星星
Rising smoke stirred the stars with a crunchy smell.
焗炉戚戚恻恻，戚戚恻恻⋯
The oven hummed. Hummed.
有如天使预早送来的福音
It was like early blessing from the angels.
好靓的晚上啊！
Such a beautiful night!
我和妈妈坐在尖东海傍
Mother and I sat at the seafront.
点点灯光在海面走来走去⋯
Lights shimmered on the sea.
美丽又温柔
Beautiful and gentle.
真的好靓！
So beautiful!
我从没吃过这么浓味的东西
I had never tasted anything so strong.
甚至杯面，烧鸭的味道也没有这么浓
Cup noodles or roast duck were not as strong.
火鸡的味道把我每一个味蕾缠住⋯
The taste embedded every single taste bud…
爆发⋯缠住⋯爆发⋯
Then exploded.
就像今晚的一切
Like everything tonight…
最靓最靓，最犀利，而且最温柔
Most beautiful, brilliant, and tender.
第二天我睡得很晏⋯
I woke up late the next day.
刷过牙我还感觉到火鸡的美味
The sweetness was still there after washing.
因为早餐吃得晚⋯
As we had a late breakfast…
午餐时妈妈只煮了罐栗米汤
There was only corn soup for lunch.
我用汤匙撩了两下
I idly found diced turkey…
竟然发现美味的火鸡粒
in the soup.
不用说，那夜就是我渴望了⋯
That night finally came the long awaited…
很久很久很久的⋯圣诞火鸡大餐！
Christmas turkey dinner!
一片片的火鸡肉和伴碟的薯仔和节瓜⋯
Slices of meat, accompanied by gourd and potato…
上面淋了老抽生粉献
Were dressed with soy sauce.
我们真的好兴奋，好满足
It was an exciting, satisfactory moment for us.
之后，我们吃了一个星期的⋯
The following week,
火鸡三文治早餐
turkey sandwich for breakfast.
星期天
Sunday,
我大着胆跟妈妈说：不如去饮茶吖
I boldly suggested eating out.
妈妈骂我「冇衣食」⋯
Mother said I was ungrateful…
不过还是带了我去饮茶
But took me out anyway.
之后，妈妈又有计⋯
Then mother got inspired again.
她把冰箱内剩下来的火鸡肉撕呀撕
What was left of the turkey was sliced…
有时候也叫我帮手撕
With me helping out at times.
火鸡留在指甲的味道
It was not easy to get rid of…
原来得洗好多次
the turkey's smell.
银芽火鸡丝炒米，好味道
Fried noodle with sliced turkey, yummy.
栗子炆火鸡丝㷛
Steaming chestnut bowl with sliced turkey.
花生火鸡骨煲粥
Peanut congee with turkey bone.
纸包火鸡包包纸
Paper turkey bun.
包火鸡包包包火鸡包
Paper turkey paper bun.
酿火鸡馅搽面包
Turkey pete with bread.
唉，我好后悔讲过一句「火鸡疴烂煮」
I shouldn't have said anything about the turkey's stomach.
端午节，当我翻开我最喜欢吃的裹蒸粽⋯
Came Dragon Boat Festival, when I dug into the dumpling…
发现咸蛋旁边是一件火鸡背的时候⋯
And found more pieces of turkey…
我脑部一时想唔通，哭起来
I lost it. I cried.
救命呀！
Oh please!
妈妈悄悄把剩下的火鸡扔掉
When mother finally disposed of the turkey…
那已经是火鸡解冻后差不多半年的事
It was already half a year later.
我的美梦跟恶梦亦同时完结
My beautiful dream ended with my nightmare.
后来我才知道⋯
Later, I learned that…
一只火鸡由出世到给人宰掉
A serving turkey needs only be raised…
也不过是几个月间的事
For a few months.
即是说，火鸡死掉后跟我们一起的日子
The time the turkey spent with us…
还要长过它的一生
Was in fact longer than its life.
我还发觉，火鸡的味道⋯
I realized also, with turkey…
将吃未吃和第一口之间已经是最高峰
Taking the first bite is all that matters.
之后的，不过是开始了也就吃下去
Afterwards, it is just "be over and done with".
我没有哲学家的头脑⋯
I am no philosopher.
不知道两件事情应该得出什么道理
I could not come up with any profundity.
可是这些想法⋯
But, such thoughts…
在我长大后⋯
After I grew up…
在一些跟圣诞节无关的日子⋯
On days unrelated to Christmas…
毫无因由的在我脑中出现过三两次
Did come up again a couple of times.
一次，是在我自己的婚宴上
Once, it was at my wedding.
一次⋯
Once…
是在我妈妈火化那天
It was at my mother's cremation.
那天，我看着天空几缕灰色的烟。
That day, I was looking at the smoke rising up.
忽然间嗅到火鸡又浓又淡的气味
Suddenly, the smell of the turkey returned.
我好后悔要妈妈扔掉最后几件火鸡。
I regretted I made mother throw the turkey away.
特别报告
"Special Report"
奥运金牌得主李丽珊决定参加今届奥运
Olympic medal winner San San Li will compete again…
向全世界人再次证明⋯
To prove to the world that…
香港运动员不是腊鸭
HK athletes are horrible.
另方面⋯
Also…
香港体运总会霍震霆⋯
The local federation…
正式向亚运协会提出申请
officially announced today:
香港将争夺下届亚运会主办权
HK will apply to host the Asian Games.
多个运动团体立即表示热烈支持
The response from all sides has been enthusiastic.
其中港九新界竹战联谊会⋯
Among them, the Bamboo Game Association…
更希望打麻将可以成为亚运项目
is proposing Mahjong for official game.
另外，全港茶餐厅员工协会⋯
While Tearoom Serving Groups…
经已发动所有会员⋯
have vowed…
争取「掷蛋挞」成为亚运比赛项目
To campaign for "Tart Throwing".
港九烧味卤味腊味同业会
As for the Cold Cut and Roasting Association…
亦向霍主席当面提出⋯
They believe…
「挂腊鸭」可以成为亚运比赛项目
"Duck Hanging" would make an ideal addition.
较为特别的是，CIC保险营业员联同⋯
More interesting, CIC Insurance is joining forces with…
大角咀春田花花幼稚园⋯
Children from…
附属小学一班小朋友⋯
Spring Flower Primary School…
争取「抢包山」
In support of…
一项几乎绝迹的运动⋯
"Bun Snatching"…
成为本港举办亚运的重点推介比赛项目
A game thought extinct.
最后⋯
In the end…
最后，一切成烟
Nothing came of anything.
最后，他们选了「掷蛋挞」做推介项目
"Tart Throwing" was chosen as the highlight.
至于香港争取申办亚运的口号⋯
As for the official slogan…
亦顺理成章叫成「香港一蛋挞」
"HK, One Big Tart" was a logical choice.
之后李丽珊蝉联失败⋯
Then San San Li lost.
亚运主办权⋯
And the hosting right of the Asian Games…
亦由一个香港人从未听过的地方夺得
Went to a place Hong Kong people have never heard of.
想着转行当运动员的茶餐厅伙记⋯
Tearoom workers, those aspiring athletes…
都回到茶餐厅继续掷他们的蛋挞
Went back to where they used to throw their tarts.
一切回复正常
Everything went on as usual.
上中学后，我再没有练习抢包手
In secondary school, I stopped practicing the 12 hands.
有时候跟妈妈饮茶⋯
Sometimes, when I went out with mother…
我都会手快快替她抢一笼大包
I'd still snatch a bun for her.
之后，茶楼再不卖大包了
Then they stopped selling buns.
点心车亦转成点心纸
Carts were replaced by ordering sheets.
一切落空
Everything came to nothing.
有时候我也会跟同学回到长洲烧烤
At times, I'd go to Cheung Chau for barbecue.
每次看见师傅⋯
The master looked older…
他都好像老了一点
Each time I saw him.
因为环保⋯
For environmental reasons…
长洲的抢包都转为塑胶
They'd changed to snatching plastic buns.
师傅说，那阵胶气，相当臭
Master thought they stunk.
长洲有个张保仔洞
On Cheung Chau was a Cheung Po Tsai Cave.
听说张保仔在洞内藏了很多宝藏
Where legend claimed a pirate hid his treasure.
因为我练过抢包手，身手比较灵活⋯
As I was the one who could crawl…
同学们叫我爬进去看看，说不定会发达
My mates said I should take a look and maybe get rich.
于是我就向着这个又黑又窄的洞⋯
So I crawled along the dark and narrow cave.
一直爬
Crawling.
洞里面什么也没有，只有一个盒
There was nothing but a box.
我小心揭开盒⋯
I opened the box…
发现里面一个没吃完的大包
Inside, there was an unfinished bun.
是不是张保仔吃过的呢？
Maybe the pirate didn't get to finish it.
「寻晚，食了六个餐包」
"Eating 6 buns last night…"
「可惜我依然系觉得仍未十分饱」
"Still left me hungry."
「寻晚，食了磅半方包」
"Eating 1½ lb white bread last night…"
「可叹是我依然觉得，不够顶肚」
"Still left me hungry."
「年少，练了六套脚法。」
"Excelled 6 sets of steps when I was young…"
「可惜我依然未觉够用。」
"Still left me empty."
「年晚，又培育了珊珊！可惜⋯」
"Brought up San San when I am old! Still…"
揸住个包，我忽然明白⋯
Bun in hand, I suddenly realized…
原来有些事情， 没有就是没有
There are things that cannot be forced.
唔得，就是唔得
A no is a no.
没有鱼蛋没有粗面没去成马尔代夫⋯
No fishball, no noodle, no Maldives…
没有奖牌没有张保仔宝藏
No medal, no pirate's treasure.
而张保仔，也没有咬过那个包
And the pirate took no bite.
原来蠢，并不那么好笑
Stupid is not funny.
蠢会失败⋯
Stupid leads to failure…
会失望
To disappointment.
失望，并不那么好笑
Disappointed is not funny.
肥，都不一定好笑
Fatness is not funny too.
肥，不一定大力
Fatness is not powerful.
大力，亦不一定得
Power doesn't mean yes.
揸住个包，我忽然想⋯
Bun in hand, I suddenly thought…
长大了，到我要面对这个实掘掘⋯
Growing up, facing this sordid world…
未必可以发梦，未必那么好笑的⋯
This not so dreamy, not so funny world…
世界的时候，我会怎么样？
What shall I be?
「⋯无力挽！」
"… Nothing shall be done!"
橙
"Powerful"
是的，我就是大个佬麦兜
Right, I am McDull the big guy.
肥，算大力
Fat, with raw power.
麻麻地可以
Not doing too well.
负家产
Negative property.
脚爪是真的大，比一节瓜还要大
With a pair of really thick calves.
脚瓜上的肌肉非常结实⋯
Very muscular…
青筋一条条凸出来，似钢筋
With steely veins running down.
至于脚趾甲⋯
As for the toenails…
有次我无无聊聊真的量了一下⋯
I got bored one time and stared at it…
足有一寸厚
They're tough, no kidding!
是的，故事讲完了
Yes, the story ends here.
这是一个尝试
This is a try.
失败⋯尝试⋯
Error… Try…
好多包⋯可是没有包保成功的故事
No guarantee that one would make it.
故事说了一轮⋯
In the end…
什么也没有？也不是
Zero gain? Not really.
就是大了双脚瓜
I have my calves.
可是楝一双脚瓜站这儿⋯
But, standing here like this…
当浪打过来⋯
When the waves hit…
那感觉还真不错
I feel great.
你知道我麻麻地叻佬，不懂得⋯
You see, smart guys like me don't really know…
替自己的故事加点教训呀锦囊呀那些
How to make a lesson out of his own story.
可是，浸一双脚瓜站水中⋯
With calves in water…
当风吹向我的脑，我会想⋯
When the wind blows, I'd think…
如果妈妈看见我这个大脚瓜⋯
If mother could see me like this…
我猜，她会好开心
She'd be happy.
不成，还是出个锦囊！
"I've come up with a lesson!"
妈妈的dot com散掉后，她又有计
Mother got inspired after her dot com failed.
她出版了一本教烹饪的食谱
She published a cookbook.
食谱最后一页教人整烧鸡
The last recipe was "Roast Chicken".
方法简单，人人可学
A simple dish no less.
「烧鸡」
"Roast Chicken".
材料是⋯鸡
Ingredient: chicken.
方法：把鸡烧几烧
Method: roast the chicken.
就这样，一味「烧鸡」大功告成
That way, you have a roast chicken.
食谱里面补充说：
There was a remark in the cookbook:
如果你想把鸡烧得美味可口⋯
If you want a delicious chicken…
吃完后不会心肺实胃气涨
A chicken that wouldn't upset you…
秘诀是：拜托，把鸡烧好一点⋯
The secret is: please, roast it well!
多谢合作！
Thank you!
麻烦你，一客常餐
One Regular, please.
常餐？常餐有什么吃？
What's a Regular?
跟特餐一样吧
The same as Special.
特餐是什么？
What's a Special?
跟快餐差不多
Same as Quickie.
快餐又是什么？
What's a Quickie?
快餐即是午餐
A Quickie is a Lunch.
午餐吃什么？
What's for Lunch?
午餐跟晚餐一样
The same as Supper.
晚餐又吃什么？
What's for Supper?
晚餐即是常餐
Same as Regular.
那么，两客常餐吧
We'll have the Regular.
今天常餐精采呀！
Our Regular today is fantastic!
对不起，常餐卖光了
Sorry, Regular is gone.
那改要特餐吧
We can have the Special.
特餐？特餐有什么吃？
What's a Special?
特餐即是午餐呀
A Special is a Lunch.
午餐又吃什么呢？
What's for Lunch?
都是晚餐那些吧
What you get for Supper.
什么是晚餐？
What's for Supper?
跟快餐一样
Same as Quickie.
快餐吃什么？
What's for Quickie?
唉，快餐不就是常餐
A Quickie is a Regular.
常餐不是卖光了吗？
But you said Regular is gone!
对，常餐卖光了，要吃特餐吗？
Regular sure is gone. How about the Special?
来两份特餐吧
It's the Special, then.
对不起，特餐卖光了
Sorry, Special is gone.
妈妈，改快餐吧
Mother, let's have the Quickie.
快餐有什么？
What's for Quickie?
快餐即是常餐
A Quickie is a Regular.
常餐又有什么呢？
What's for Regular?
常餐即是午餐
A Regular is a Lunch.
那么午餐又有什么吃？
What's for Lunch?
午餐跟晚餐一样
Same as Supper.
晚餐呢？
And Supper?
晚餐不就是特餐
Supper is like Special.
不是说特餐卖光了吗？
But you said the Special is gone.
特餐卖光了，要试试快餐吗？都一样的
The Special sure is gone. Try Quickie. It's the same.
来两份快餐吧
We'll have Quickie.
对不起，没快餐了
Sorry, Quickie is gone.
太过分了吧？你们究竟有吃的没？
This is too much! Is there anything we can eat here?
午餐吧，午餐精采呀
Try the Lunch. It's fantastic!
怎么个精采法？
How so?
跟晚餐一样精采
It's like the Supper.
晚餐又怎样呢？
What about the Supper?
跟常餐一样精采
It's like the Regular.
常餐又怎样呢？
And what about the Regular?
常餐早卖光了，你说精采不？
The Regular is gone. Isn't that fantastic?
好吧好吧！两份午餐好了
Great! We'll have Lunch.
对不起，午餐卖光了
Sorry, Lunch is gone.
要试试我们的晚餐吗？都一样的
Try our Supper. It's all the same.
光天白日，吃什么鬼晚餐？
I'm not having supper under broad daylight!
唉，说是说晚餐，还不就是午餐？
What's in a name? It's the same as Lunch.
好吧好吧，拜托！两份晚餐！快！
Great! Whatever you say! And make it quick!
要快吗？那得吃快餐了！
You want it quick? Try Quickie!